A Guide to the Vaughan Family Papers, 1943-1946
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Vaughan Family Papers 1943-1946
Thomas Balch Library
M 007
1 cu. ft.
This collection consists of letters exchanged between James Millard Vaughan and his mother, Fannie Vaughan, friends, and relatives during his service in the Army in World War II. It also includes correspondence between his mother and her friends and relatives during that time. The collection includes World War II memorabilia such as postcards, greeting cards, a ration book, and "Personna Blade Mail." The correspondence covers life, as it existed during the war. Of interest is the relating of daily activities and rationing of products.
James M. Vaughan
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research
Acquisition Information
James M. Vaughan, Purcellville, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2004.0074
Biographical Information
James Millard Vaughan, also known as Perch, Tunney, and Jimmy, was the son of Francis Edna and Clifton Mahlon Vaughan. His mother, Francis Miller, was born in 1891 and married (1) Robert "Bobby" Reybold, (2) Clifton Vaughan, and (3) John H. Monroe. His father was born in 1875 and died 11 April 1945 while James M. was in the service.
Frances and Clifton had four children,
Virginia born 1916, married Chester Gordon
Thurburt born 1917, married Clara Horn
Louise born 1919, married Harry Cannon
James Millard, born 28 April 1921 in Purcellville, VA, married Annabelle Lamb. James M. and Annabelle had one son, James Woodford "Woody" Vaughan, born 14 November 1951.
James M. was inducted into the U. S. Army at Camp Lee, VA 29 December 1942, and served as a power plant operator in the 840th Antiaircraft Artillery Battalion. He was separated at Fort Bragg, NC 30 January 1946.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of letters exchanged between James Millard Vaughan and his mother, Fannie Vaughan, friends, and relatives during his service in the Army in World War II. It also includes correspondence between his mother and her friends and relatives during that time. The collection includes World War II memorabilia such as postcards, greeting cards, a ration book, and "Personna Blade Mail." The correspondence covers life, as it existed during the war. Of interest is the relating of daily activities and rationing of products.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
The Blue Ridge Herald
1930 US Census Virginia
Deborah Lee, PhD., Purcellville, VA
Other Finding Aid
None
Related Material
None
Contents List
- Correspondence, F.E. Vaughan to J.M. Vaughan, Ft. Eustis, VA, 1943 (Box:folder 1:1)
- Correspondence, F.E. Vaughan to J.M. Vaughan, Camp Stewart, GA, Jul 1943-18 Jan 1944 (Box:folder 1:2)
- Correspondence, F.E. Vaughan to J.M. Vaughan, Westhampton Beach, NY, 20 Jan 1944-12 May 1944 (Box:folder 1:3)
- Correspondence, F.E. Vaughan to J.M. Vaughan, Camp Stewart, GA, 13 May 1944-23 Aug 1944 (Box:folder 1:4)
- Correspondence, Mrs. Harvey Cannon (Lou) sister to J.M. Vaughan, 14 Jan 1943-10 Mar 1944 (Box:folder 1:5)
- Correspondence, Mrs. Chester Gordon (Virginia) sister to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 1:6)
- Correspondence, M.T. Vaughan brother to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 1:7)
- Correspondence, WW II Memorabilia, n.d. (Box:folder 1:8)
- Correspondence, WW II Postcards, n.d. (Box:folder 1:9)
  Postcards
  Genesee Street, Greene, NY
  Purcellville, VA
  Bear's Den near Purcellville, VA
  Business Section of Hinesville, GA near Camp Stewart
- Correspondence, J.M. Vaughan to F.E. Vaughan, 17 Jan 1943-24 Dec 1943 (Box:folder 2:1)
  Postcard
  United States Army
- Correspondence, J.M. Vaughan to F.E. Vaughan, 4 Jan 1944-29 Dec 1944 (Box:folder 2:2)
- Correspondence, J.M. Vaughan to F.E. Vaughan, 1 Jan 1945-31 Mar 1945 (Box:folder 2:3)
- Correspondence, J.M. Vaughan to F.E. Vaughan, 1 Apr 1945-31 Jul 1945 (Box:folder 2:4)
- Correspondence, J.M. Vaughan to F.E. Vaughan, 1 Aug 1945-9 Jan 1946 (Box:folder 2:5)
- Correspondence, M.T. Vaughan Family to F.E. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 2:6)
- Correspondence, Daughters Virginia and Louise to F.E. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 2:7)
- Correspondence, Friends to F.E. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 2:8)
  Rehoboth Beach, Delaware
- Correspondence, Letter to Pvt. Walter Bown from wife, n.d. (Box:folder 2:9)
- Correspondence, Sympathy cards, Death of husband Clifton to F.E. Vaughan, 13 Apr 1945-2 May 1945 (Box:folder 2:10)
- Correspondence, Household Papers, 1943 (Box:folder 2:11)
- Correspondence, Wedding and Graduation announcements, 1944-1945 (Box:folder 2:12)
- Correspondence, Friends to J.M. Vaughan, (A-H), n.d. (Box:folder 3:1)
  Christmas in Purcellville, Virginia
- Correspondence, Friends to J.M. Vaughan, (I-Z), n.d. (Box:folder 3:2)
- Correspondence, Hazel Ashby to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 3:3)
- Correspondence, John (Billy) Buxton to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 3:4)
  St. Mary's Catholic Church, St. Petersburg, Florida
  Trailer Park, Florida
  Georgia State Capitol, Atlanta, Georgia
- Correspondence, James Colbert Family to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 3:5)
- Correspondence, Dottie Keckley to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 3:6)
- Correspondence, Doris Kelley to J. M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 3:7)
- Correspondence, Genevieve Lemon to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 3:8)
- Correspondence, W.E. Miller to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 3:9)
- Correspondence, Jean Morehead to J.M. Vaughan, n.d. (Box:folder 3:10)
  "How about letting me hear from you?"
- Correspondence, Greeting Cards for Servicemen, 1943 - 1946 (Box:folder 3:11)
- Correspondence, Photographs, n.d. (Box:folder 3:12)
  Photographs
  James M. Vaughan at home 130 N. 18th St., Purcellville, VA
  James M. Vaughan in the Army
  James M. Vaughan with car
  James M. Vaughan in Army with cigarette
  James M. Vaughan and mother Fannie
  James M. Vaughan in front of home with car
  James M. Vaughan with 50 cal. Machine gun antiaircraft, GA
  James Woodford Vaughan at Lou's house
  James M. Vaughan at Lou's house
  James M. and Annabell Vaughan
  Portrait of James M. Vaughan
  Woody Vaughan, 14 months old
  James M. Vaughan with Fannie his mother and Louise his sister